Finding Aid for Jean Ledwith King Oral History Collection
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Jean Ledwith King Oral History Collection circa 1927-2011, 2011
Owens, John
62.7 GB online
2014049 Aa 3
Ann Arbor, Michigan attorney who spent her career fighting sex discrimination in education, sports, and politics. The collection contains oral history interviews, tribute statements, and photographs collected on the occasion of renaming the Women's Center of Southeastern Michigan after Jean Ledwith King and for the creation of a documentary, "The Power of One: Celebrating Jean Ledwith King," by John Owens.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Materials donated by John Owens (Donor no. 11087 ) in April 2014.
No further additions to the records are expected.
This material is available for research only in the Reading Room of the Bentley Historical Library at the University of Michigan (Ann Arbor, MI).
Jean Ledwith King was born in Chicago, Illinois in 1924. She attended the University of Michigan for college, met her husband, John King, and in 1948 graduated with a bachelor's degree in English. In 1953, she earned a master's degree in history. She was involved in politics and, in her 40s, decided to apply to law school. She attended the University of Michigan Law School, graduated in 1968, and passed the bar exam in 1970.
As an attorney, King quickly made her mark fighting sex discrimination, particularly in education. In 1970, she filed a complaint against the University of Michigan for sex discrimination, which resulted in the government withholding funds from various federal contracts until practices improved. King's efforts helped women organize to fight discrimination both formally and informally at institutions throughout Michigan and the United States.
King has also been instrumental in furthering women's opportunities in athletics, beginning in the mid-1970s. One of her toughest cases was the suit against Michigan State University in 1979 for discriminating against women in the unequal treatment of the men's and women's basketball teams. Over the course of her career, King has fought for women's participation in over 30 different sports.
In 2011, the Women's Center of Southeastern Michigan officially changed its name to the Jean Ledwith King Women's Center of Southeastern Michigan to honor King and further frame their own mission and identity in light of King's work and values. To celebrate this, documentary filmmaker John Owens worked to compile oral histories from King and various other individuals associated with her work for the creation of a short documentary entitled "The Power of One: Celebrating Jean Ledwith King." This film, in addition to a compilation of brief statements from politicians, female athletes, and a former law partner, was shown at the dinner held on March 26, 2011 to commemorate the Women's Center's name change (see Frank Weir, "Ann Arbor Legend Honored," Grand Rapids Legal News, April 2011; Mary Morgan, "Honoring Jean Ledwith King," Ann Arbor Chronicle, March 2011).
The collection is organized by format into two series, Video Recordings and Photographs.
The Jean Ledwith King Oral History Collection is composed of visual materials collected by John Owens to celebrate King's life and work in 2011, when the Women's Center of Southeast Michigan was renamed in King's honor.
Subjects:
Jean Ledwith King Women's Center of Southeast Michigan.; King, Jean Ledwith.; Michigan State University.; Sex discrimination against women--Michigan.; Sex discrimination in sports--Michigan.; University of Michigan.; Women lawyers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women's rights--Michigan.
Contributors:
Allen, Knatarsha.; Burton, Carol W.; Cumming, Kimberli.; Francis, Nancy C.; George, Maryanne.; Hollenshead, Carol.; Hutchins, Carol.; Maynard, Olivia.; Neiberg, Vicki.; Rivers, Lynn N.; Sandler, Bernice Resnick.; Traxinger, Deb.
Genre Terms:
Digital images.; Digital moving image formats.; Interviews.; Oral histories.
- Video Recordings 2010-2011
  The Video Recordings series (2010-2011, 62.4 GB) contains digital moving image files and is arranged by genre into three subseries: Documentary, Interviews, and Tribute Statements. The Documentary subseries contains two versions of "The Power of One: Celebrating Jean Ledwith King" created by John Owens. The Interviews subseries consists of oral history interviews conducted with King and various individuals familiar with King and her work, including some of those involved with particular cases, such as two members of the Michigan State University Women's Basketball team in the late 1970s. The Tribute Statements subseries includes statements from politicians, female athletes, and a former law partner honoring King and her impact, particularly with regard to women in politics and sports. Some of the digital file names in this series have been changed for consistency with spelling found in other sources.
  - Documentary, .MP4 and .MOV files
    [Online access restricted to computers in Bentley, Duderstadt Center, Hatcher, and Shapiro Libraries on University of Michigan campus.]
    - Final version of "The Power of One: Celebrating Jean Ledwith King," 2011
    - Longer version of "The Power of One: Celebrating Jean Ledwith King," 2011
  - Interviews
    - Allen, Knatarsha (Legal Assistant) 2011, .MP4 and .MOV files
    - Burton, Carol (mother of Tricia McNaughton) 2011, .MP4 and .MOV files
    - Cumming, Kimberli (Executive Director, Women's Center of Southeastern Michigan) 2011, .MP4 and .MOV files
    - Francis, Nancy (Judge, Washtenaw County Trial Court) 2011, .MP4 and .MOV files
    - George, Maryanne (Reporter for the Detroit Free Press, 1980-2006), 2011, .MP4 and .MOV files
    - Hollenshead, Carol (Director Emeritus, University of Michigan Center for the Education of Women) 2011, .MP4 and .MOV files
    - Hutchins, Carol (Michigan State University Basketball Player, 1976-1979) 2011, .MP4 and .MOV files
    - King, Jean Ledwith 2011, .MP4 and .MOV files
    - Maynard, Olivia [Libby] (Chair, Michigan Democratic Party, 1979-1983) 2011, .MP4 and .MOV files
    - Neiberg, Vicki (Michigan State University Alliance to End Sex Discrimination, 1970s) 2011, .MP4 and .MOV files
    - Rivers, Lynn (Law Clerk, 1989-1991) 2011, .MP4 and .MOV files
    - Sandler, Bernice (Senior Scholar, Women's Research & Education Institute) 2011, .MP4 and .MOV files
    - Traxinger, Deb (Michigan State University Basketball Player, 1978-1982) 2011, .MP4 and .MOV files
  - Tribute Statements
    - Compilations 2011, .MP4 and .MOV files
    - Bloch, Rich (former Law Partner) 2011, .MP4 and .M4V files
    - Foudy, Julie (U.S. Olympic Soccer Gold Medalist) 2011, .MP4 and .MOV files
    - Levin, Carl (U.S. Senator for Michigan) 2011, .MP4 and .MPG files
    - Ruggiero, Angela (U.S. Olympic Hockey Gold Medalist) 2011, .MP4 and .MOV files
    - Stabenow, Debbie (U.S. Senator for Michigan) 2011, .MP4 and .MOV files
- Photographs, circa 1927-2011, .ZIP file
  The Photographs series (circa 1927-2011, 307 MB) contains digital images related to Jean Ledwith King and her legacy. Arranged in folders and compiled as part of the creation of John Owens's documentary on King, the series includes images of King from the 1920s to the 2010s as well as various photographs and newspaper clippings relating to particular cases and issues.
  - 1972 Democratic Convention
  - Bentley
  - Jean Family Photos
  - JLK Digital Photos
  - MSU Basketball
  - Tricia Sanders
  - Women & Sports
  - Women's Political Caucus